DES Action USA records, 1939-2016 (bulk 1975-2014)
Sophia Smith Collection
DES Action USA records
1939-2016
1975-2014
DES Action National (Organization)
739
24 boxes (9.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
DES Action USA is a national consumer advocacy group, whose mission is to educate and raise awareness about diethylstilbestrol (DES), an oral synthetic estrogen drug; and support and advocate for the DES-exposed population. The DES Action USA records are primarily comprised of materials documenting the activities, programs, and projects of the organization.
Historical Note
DES Action USA is a national consumer advocacy group, whose mission is to educate and raise awareness about diethylstilbestrol (DES) in the public and medical and legal professions, support the DES-exposed population, and advocate for consumer vigilance and rights. DES is a synthetic estrogen, which was, from about 1940, prescribed to women at risk of miscarriage and, later, to promote healthy babies. Medical research has now shown that DES has adverse effects and that the approximately 10 million DES-exposed people are at risk for cancer, infertility, pregnancy complications, and other health problems.
The drug came onto the United States market in 1940 from several manufacturers, as the drug was both unpatented and cheap to produce. Despite research demonstrating possible carcinogenic effects (documented in the 1930s) and its inefficacy for preventing miscarriage in 1953, pharmaceutical companies publicized earlier and more favorable studies in their marketing and promotion. In 1971, medical researchers identified several clusters of rare vaginal cancers in some of the children exposed to DES in utero, now teenagers and young adults. The news was alarming to many of the women who had taken the drug during their pregnancies. As the women's health movement was developing during the same years, concerned women around the country used the model of local organizing and outreach to find other DES-exposed women and their children (known as DES mothers, sons, and daughters).
One of the earliest gatherings was of the DES Information Group, founded by Pat Cody (1923-2010) in 1974, working with the Berkeley Free Clinic in California. Cody's group soon joined with the DES Action Committee of the San Francisco-based Committee for the Medical Rights of Women, and the two groups merged into a Bay-area organization. Similar grassroots organizations were being started in Connecticut, Illinois, Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, and Pennsylvania. DES Action National (later renamed DES Action USA) formed in 1977 with a meeting of these grassroots groups. The organization incorporated as a non-profit in 1979.
Much of DES Action USA's early work was at local and state levels. Public health grants and legislative efforts supported educational outreach and medical care in California and New York. DES Action USA also successfully lobbied that a Federal Task Force be established. During the 1980s, work at state and national levels resulted in several official National DES Awareness Weeks (1983-1985), continued educational work and outreach efforts, and support for liability litigation cases against manufacturers.
Aware of the need for national funding for DES research and education, director Nora Cody (daughter of Pat Cody) worked closely with Representative Louise M. Slaughter (D-NY) to draft and support a research bill during the early 1990s. The bill was signed into law in 1992, with a second bill passed in 1998 to support research on the third generation of DES-affected people (the grandchildren of DES mothers). Through the early 2000s, their most high-profile work involved working with the Centers for Disease Control to develop and distribute consumer and health professional medical education materials to communicate the latest research about continuing effects of DES exposure.
The consequences of DES are now seen as a warning of the potential effects of environmental endocrine contamination. The drug was also used as a growth promoter in meat animals, and, though FDA approval for its use in animal feed was revoked in 1979, DES was found in exported American beef as recently as 2000. Other estrogenic compounds like bisphenol A are structurally similar to DES and may have similar effects.
In 2014, DES Action USA, facing the aging of its leadership, chose to merge with another medical nonprofit, the MedShadow Foundation, which does similar educational and outreach work but focuses on the risks and long-term adverse effects of many prescription drugs. The decision allowed the DES Action USA Board to step down from administration, while allowing DES Action USA to continue its work and mission.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The DES Action USA Records consist of 9.75 linear feet, dating from 1938-2016, with the bulk of the records dating from 1978-2014. The collection is comprised primarily of records documenting the activities, programs, and projects of DES Action USA over a forty-five-year period. Types of material include correspondence, Board of Directors meeting minutes, annual reports, membership and fundraising files, material from conferences and meetings, Senate and House testimonies and legislation, legal documents and court cases, contracts and educational materials, program descriptions and reports, publications, press coverage, medical research literature, pharmaceutical company research, photographs, audiovisual materials, and a small selection of artifacts and oversize posters. There are two boxes (0.6 linear ft) of materials that are restricted, as they house personal health information.
The records are arranged in nine series:
I. ADMINISTRATION
II. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS
III. LEGISLATION AND LITIGATION
IV. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
V. OUTREACH
VI. MEDICAL CORRESPONDENCE AND RESEARCH DATA [RESTRICTED]
VII. DIETHYLSTILBESTROL SUBJECT FILES
VIII. AUDIOVISUAL AND PHOTOGRAPHIC MEDIA
IX. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
These records provide information on diethylstilbestrol, patient and consumer advocacy, and product liability litigation. They reflect DES Action USA's long history of focused activism as support and information providers. Records that explore the medical and social effects of DES exposure and its consequences (cancer, infertility, pregnancy complications, immune dysfunction, gender identity, the psychological effects of risk awareness) are of particular value. Documents related to pharmaceutical litigation are of interest because of the legal precedents for product liability that resulted. The medical and health education publications document changing awareness of women's and men's reproductive health issues, while the organization's sustained local and national coordination offers a model to activists in opposition to corporate interests. Publications include a complete run of their newsletter, Pat Cody's book, DES Voices: From Anger to Action (2006), and two community organizing handbooks (1980, 1985). Photographs document conferences and meetings, while slides and videotapes document health education work and public outreach.
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exceptions:
Researchers are required to sign a Records Access Agreement agreeing not to identify individuals named in letters or emails written to DES Action USA.
Series VII. MEDICAL CORRESPONDENCE AND RESEARCH DATA is closed until 2037.
Access to audiovisual materials requires the production of access copies.
Periodic additions to this collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
DES Action USA donated their records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2015.
DES-exposed daughters; DES-exposed sons; DES-exposed persons; Diethylstilbestrol--Law and legislation--United States; Diethylstilbestrol--Side effects; Feminism--Health aspects; Health care reform; Health education of women--United States; Intersex people--United States; Prenatal care--United States--History; Products liability--Drugs--United States; Public health--United States; Reproductive health--United States--History; Transgender people--United States; Women--Health and hygiene--United States; Women's health services--United States
Related material may be found in the National Women's Health Network records and the Reproductive Rights National Network records, both housed at Smith College Special Collections.
Select news clippings have been separated from the collection, as they are readily available via Neilson Library, Interlibrary Loan, or originating news sites. For a list of these separated clippings, please contact Special Collections for a copy.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION (1974-2014), 1.33 linear ft.
  This series concerns the founding, early planning, and history of DES Action USA. It is arranged chronologically within several subseries and sub-subseries. It contains early planning documents, correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, governance documents, local and regional affiliate records, and biographical material about the leadership.
  The first subseries, History, contains records of the early years of DES Action when it was part of the Committee for the Medical Rights of Women. Also included are several organizational histories and timelines.
  The second subseries, Board of Directors, contains meeting minutes and reports from various committees and projects, correspondence, manuals, and profiles of Kari Christianson, Pat Cody, Nora Cody, and Fran Howell, all founders or long-term leaders of the organization. Materials are arranged chronologically, save for the biographical files, which are alphabetical by name. The discussions reveal tensions about support for litigation, the independence of affiliates, and the challenges of maintaining vision and activism over decades. The minutes also show the changing needs of members over time, as cancer fears shifted to other concerns like infertility, pregnancy complications, and other medical and personal issues.
  The folder, "Minutes and reports, 2001-02," contains a significant discussion of reports and potential research concerning DES effects on gender identity and sexual orientation among DES Daughters and Sons in the 2001-2002 Board meeting minutes. The discussion includes email conversations with the DES Sons Network, an informal group led by Michael Freilick, a DES Action Board member, about inadequate representation and attention to DES-exposed men's issues, including hypogonadism, infertility, testicular cancer, intersex and transgender identity.
  The Organization subseries documents the organization's incorporation as a non-profit, and is comprised of by-laws, amendments, and other governance documents. The subseries also documents the working relationship between regional affiliates and the national Board. The annual reports summarize projects and activities that are more extensively documented in SERIES III. LEGISLATION AND LITIGATION, SERIES IV. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS, and SERIES V. OUTREACH.
- SERIES II. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS (1979-2014), 0.5 linear ft.
  This series is divided into two subseries, Membership and Fundraising. Material is arranged chronologically. Within Membership, there is correspondence from members in response to renewal requests or articles in the DES Action Voice newsletter (See SERIES V. OUTREACH, subseries Public for newsletter issues). The letters primarily date from 2006-2014. In addition, there are sample membership renewal letters dating from 1995-2005, which reflect the type of requests sent to members.
  The Fundraising subseries documents the wide range of sources DES Action USA has relied on for funding over the years. Member support was central to sustaining the organization, as reflected in the folders of special appeal mailings. A number of these letters had attached sticky notes recording the number of letters sent for different campaigns; these numbers have been transcribed onto the documents.
  Two folders contain material about the support of actor Jean Kasem, a DES daughter and wife of radio personality Casey Kasem. She was involved with DES Action USA from 1990-1992, and recorded a series of public service announcements for television for the organization. Photographs of Jean, Casey, and their daughter Liberty Kasem, along with video recordings of the announcements are located in SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
  This series is also comprised of a selection of grant proposals and documentation of grant funding from several family foundations. See SERIES V. OUTREACH, subseries Health Education Contracts, for the records of government-funded grants at the state and federal levels.
- SERIES III. LEGISLATION AND LITIGATION (1978-2010), 0.65 linear ft.
  Included in this series are materials related to the DES Action USA legislative and litigation efforts. Materials are arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  The Federal Legislation subseries contains material on a number of national legislative efforts, such as securing funding and product liability reform. During the 1980s, there were three annual "National DES Awareness Weeks" officially proclaimed by Congress and President Reagan. When Nora Cody became executive director in 1990, she began working with members of the House of Representatives and the Senate to secure funding for research on the long-term effects of DES exposure. A partnership between Representative Louise M. Slaughter (D-NY), a DES daughter, and DES Action USA led to designated funding for DES research in 1992. Correspondence and documentation related to this legislative efforts are documented in this series. Other legislative activism documents a continued fight against weakening product liability law. DES Action USA fought against bills like the 1995 "Product Liability Fairness Act," which would have eliminated manufacturer liability for any FDA-approved product. Similar efforts are seen in the subseries State Legislation. (Both California and New York passed DES-related funding laws circa 1980-1982.)
  DES cases have created legal precedents concerning product liability and medical ethics. The Litigation subseries pertains to educational materials about litigation produced by DES Action USA, articles, correspondence, and court records relating to DES cases in the courts. The subseries also has information about the organization referring members and inquirers to several lawyers who developed expertise on the issues. Several folders concern Washington, D.C. lawyer Aaron Levine, who built his practice around medical liability and women's health issues, including a number of DES cases. There are also files about lawyer Sybil Shainwald, who also litigated DES cases.
- SERIES IV. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS (1979-2001), 0.25 linear ft.
  This series contains records of annual meetings for members and external conferences attended, supported, or convened by DES Action USA. Material is arranged chronologically. The material about annual meetings includes ephemera, such as agendas and information packs, provided to participants, as well as conference proceedings and transcripts of lectures and presentations. There are meeting-related photographs in SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
  The first scientific meeting that DES Action USA participated in was 1979. "Estrogens and the Environment" was hosted by the National Institute for Environmental Health Sciences in North Caroline, and Pat Cody was invited to give a poster presentation. She met several researchers at that meeting who would continue working closely with DES Action USA for the next several decades. There is a folder containing the conference agenda and summaries of the presentations given. Other external conferences included the 1985 United Nations Conference on Women's Health, held in Kenya. Pat Cody attended and gave a talk about DES, and there are samples of multilingual brochures about DES produced for the conference.
  DES Action USA also sponsored several research conferences, and there are agendas, proceedings, and planning documents for both the DES Research Update 1999: Current Knowledge, Future Directions conference and the 2001 DES Action International Colloquium: Discovery, Education, Science. Like the annual meetings, there are photographs in SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES V. OUTREACH (1957-2016), 2.3 linear feet
  The majority of DES Action USA's work is documented in this series. It has been arranged into subseries; each subseries has been arranged into sub-subseries by contract, project, or type of material. The three subseries, Health Education Contracts, Public, and Medical Professionals, contain records about and samples of work produced by DES Action USA in their outreach work. Health Education Contracts covers the major government-funded work performed by the organization. Their first contract in 1979 was awarded during their transition from being part of the Committee for the Medical Rights of Women to an independent organization. The contract was through the Northern California Cancer Program, and was funded by the National Cancer Institute. The educational project secured enough funding to allow Pat Cody and Nancy Adess to become paid staff working full-time on DES issues instead of being informal volunteers. The files contain a copy of the original contract, educational program drafts and flyers, and scripts for the "Ask Your Mother: Finding the DES-Exposed" slide-tape program. The slides and the audio recording are located in SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS. The presentation was given to Bay-area family planning clinics, and shared with other health organizations.
  Included in the materials are samples of the educational literature produced by DES Action USA, including a 1980 handbook, Community Organizing for Health, which presented DES Action as a model for other community health groups. The women's health centers opening across the country during the 1970s proved to be critical to their educational work, as they provided a ready network for sharing literature and information about DES exposure with their communities. The organization's first health education contract led to a more substantial agreement funded by the state of California. This contract was a continuation of the work begun in 1978 and took effect in 1982. The "Ask Your Mother" slideshow was expanded into fuller training workshops for health professionals, educational literature included the creation of new brochures, posters, and a telephone information line. Several of these posters are included in SERIES IX. OVERSIZE. There is a small folder about the second National Cancer Institute pilot project in 1995 in Massachusetts that focused on continuing medical education for health care providers.
  Finally, there are nine folders of material about DES Action USA's most substantial contract: a contract with the Centers for Disease Control (CDC). Working with Senator Tom Harkin (D-IA) and again with Rep. Slaughter (D-NY), funding was secured in 1998 for further public education about continued effects of DES. DES Action USA received funding for an education campaign targeted to both health professionals and the general public. The campaign happened throughout 2003. The project records include a planning research report; a handbook for affiliate groups to support local outreach; professional and lay educational literature; notes and agendas for a series of teleconference calls hosted by CDC researchers; and the CDC DES Update information book. In SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS, there are two computer CD-ROMs containing a continual medical education program produced out by DES Action USA as part of the campaign.
  The Public subseries is the largest of the three subseries. It covers media campaigns, press coverage, educational literature, DES Action USA publications, and writing by DES Action USA members. The first two sub-subseries document media campaigns, press releases, and subsequent press coverage. For long-term preservation, photocopies of newspaper clippings have been made for articles unavailable in other formats, while articles available through Neilson Library or the Five Colleges library system are noted in a bibliography (Appendix 1). There is one article on oversize paper that is located in the flat file.
  The media campaigns sub-subseries covers both political actions, as well as educational efforts. Documents include correspondence, flyers, posters, press releases, and background packets about the organization and DES. Four folders contain material from individual campaigns from 1979-1984 and 2004 (arranged chronologically), and two folders hold press releases from 1990-2000. Additional posters and objects can be found in SERIES IX. OVERSIZE.
  Press coverage of DES Action USA includes member profiles in local or regional papers, coverage of litigation and legislation, and general publicity about DES, including coverage resulting from media campaigns or occasions like the National DES Awareness Weeks. Articles are from newspapers, magazines, and newsletters, and are arranged chronologically. Items of note include early coverage of the cancer link discovery, articles in national women's magazines like Redbook, and newspaper op-ed pieces by Representative Louise Slaughter and author Anna Quindlen. More information about political and court efforts can be found in SERIES III. LEGISLATION AND LITIGATION.
  The educational literature sub-subseries contains educational packets sent to inquirers, graphics and associated reproduction licenses for cartoons and DES advertisements, DES Action USA-produced ephemera-dating from their first pamphlet (which pre-dates the national organization) through the mid-1990s, and similar ephemera published by government agencies and other community health organizations.
  A complete run (1978-2014) of the DES Action USA newsletter, DES Action Voice, is included, followed by two issues from 2016 (after the transition to new administration). There is also a sample production folder for an issue from 2009, containing story ideas, correspondence, and editing files, which documents their usual process for creating issues. One unique aspect of their newsletter is their commitment to explaining medical research findings to their public audience. In 2009, Pat Cody created a handwritten index to the medical literature covered in the DES Action Voice over the years, which is included in these files. The newsletter documents the activities of the organization both regionally and nationally, and includes letters from members about issues of concern or in response to previous articles.
  The remainder of the Public subseries contains writing by members of DES Action USA. There were two books published. One is a photo-essay by Margaret Lee Braun that developed from a traveling exhibit that was hosted at Smith College in 1993, among other locations. The book, DES Stories, was published in 2001, and a galley copy of the manuscript, in addition to other publication correspondence and publicity flyers, is included. The second book, DES Voices: From Anger to Action, is Pat Cody's history of DES and the organization's work over the years. These files include five folders of background research materials, which have been left in Cody's original order, a draft of the manuscript, publication files, flyers, and a copy of the published book.